You have to track dangerous animals, then get close to them without being attacked.
It takes people with a very special mix of determination and dedication.
Unbelievable!
Thousands try, but very few can do it.
Now the BBC has chosen nine animal lovers from ordinary backgrounds to see if any of them has what it takes to become a wildlife film-maker.
This week, the three remaining competitors battle it out in the final, in big-cat country.
I'm really nervous now.
They must master the art of filming the fastest and most powerful predators in Africa.
One person will get a job with the BBC's Natural History Unit.
For the winner, this will be their wildest dream come true.
Its vast plains are home to many of Africa's most amazing animals, but it's most famous for its big cats and the prides of lions that make it one of the best wildlife locations in the world.
Welcome to the final.
And welcome to the Masai Mara.
I'm well excited.
I should hope you are well excited!
'I'm Nick Knowles, and I've been keeping an eye on the competitors 'as they're tried to prove they've got what it takes to win a job with the BBC's Natural History Unit.'
Look!
That's a pocket-sized elephant.
This is the final test for Cherylin, Anna and Allen.
Over the weeks, they've been assessed by some of the world's most knowledgeable animal experts, led by film-maker James Honeyborne.
He's been making award-winning wildlife programmes for the BBC for more than 20 years.
He's the man our three finalists need to impress.
I think filming in the Masai Mara is the ultimate wildlife filming test.
Welcome to our bush camp, your home for these last five days.
You're going to have to keep your wits about you to get through this week.
Just three tents left.
Pick one and get yourself settled in.
It's pretty cool being in the Masai Mara.
There's great wildlife.
There's a... great big hippo walking behind me.
Last week, the competitors aimed to book their place in the final by making a film about a conservation success story in just two days.
Anna and Cherylin worked together and focused on the endangered black rhino.
And they couldn't believe what was waiting for them.
Oh, my goodness, look at that!
Allen and Lucy were the other team and chose the rare Grevy's zebra as their subject.
But some fascinating and ferocious lion behaviour stopped them in their tracks.
Incredible!
Awesome.
What an amazing thing to see!
Anna and Cherylin kept searching for stories, and found out about a leopard capture and release from a local village.
That was very cool.
Lucy and Allen were sent to find cheetahs in a last-chance challenge.
Emotionally, it's exhausting, and the thought of going home is horrible.
I don't want to go home.
And then James had to make his biggest decision so far.
The person we're going to take through... ..is Allen.
Allen had booked himself a place in the final.
I know Cherylin wants this.
She wants it badly.
And I know Anna wants this.
It's why we're all here.
But I know one thing for sure - I want it more than them!
I've said it all along.
For the person who gets the job at the end of it, it's going to change their life for ever.
It's home to massive amounts of wildlife.
It hosts the biggest wildlife spectacle on the planet - the wildebeest migration.
It's also hosted the BBC for over a decade, making the Big Cat Diary.
They usually hunt as a team, meaning they can bring down prey far heavier than themselves.
Then there's the world's fastest land mammal, the cheetah.
They can accelerate from 0-70mph in just three seconds.
On average, every other chase results in a kill.
To get shots like these, taken by professionals, requires a good eye, a steady hand and nerves of steel.
This week we're joined by a man who knows the Masai Mara inside out, Big Cat Diary presenter Jonathan Scott.
I don't believe it!
He's lived and worked in Kenya for decades.
I can see by your smiles that you recognise our distinguished expert, so I'm sure you're very pleased that he's along with us for the week.
Let me tell you about your final assignment.
Each of you has to make a film... ..on the Masai Mara that's based around its most famous residents, the big cats.
Each of you will have a day to direct a film, and each of you will be able to use your fellow aspiring film-makers in whatever role you see fit.
And you have to choose a theme for your film - predator, survival, family.
Because the BBC has made so many programmes here, film-makers can now recognise many of the big cats, and have even given names to those that have been featured regularly in series like Big Cat Diary.
If you are just heading out that way, into the open, you're already in Marsh pride territory.
You're also in the territory of Honey's boys, the three male cheetahs.
If you were to go beyond them, you would be in Shakira's territory, with her three cubs.
So as far as big cats are concerned, you are in the right place.
Remember, you're in competition for the one big prize - a job with the Natural History Unit.
We expect big things of you this week.
'Each finalist will have one day to make their film.
'They can use the other two competitors to help them, 'as camera operators, spotters or as researchers.'
James has decided that each finalist must make their film from footage shot on the day when they're in charge.
He'll be assessing how each finalist performs then and, crucially, when they're working for the others, too.
It's the toughest challenge they've faced.
I'm really nervous now.
I never get nervous, and I'm like...
This week, it's really pulling together everything that's happened before, so it's bringing together those skills, those experiences.
They know the bush craft and the field skills, they know how to use a camera.
They can make a good film.
Cherylin will be taking charge tomorrow, and has already picked a theme for her film - family.
I'm very interested in particular in cheetahs.
My plan is to look at sibling bonding.
But although Anna and Allen will be working for Cherylin tomorrow, she's chosen a surprising way of briefing her team.
Right, then, guys.
What I'm looking for is the interactions.
Have you got a story in your head of what you want?
I have.
Right.
So...
I'm not sharing that.
I'll just use the initiative and...
I know that.
I trust you 100%.
Right.
'At the end of the day, it's a competition,' and they don't need to know the story, because if I've asked them to follow a group of animals, and I want them to film the interactions, they can work it out for themselves.
It's just after dawn in the Masai Mara, and Cherylin will have the whole day to make her film.
Jonathan will be with her, too, assessing how she performs in an area he knows well.
He'll then report back to James.
Cherylin wants to make a film with the theme of family, and has sent 19-year-old Anna to track down the Marsh pride of lions.
I'm going to see pussy cats!
Allen will hunt for the three cheetah brothers, while Cherylin herself will search the vast plains for the female cheetah, Shakira, and her cubs.
You can't write her off, because you would have written her off in the first, second, third, fourth week, and here she is in the final, so who knows what she's capable of.
39-year-old Cherylin has always been determined to change her life for the better.
I was a manager in a fast-food restaurant and one day I thought, "Do you know what?
"I don't care how much money I earn.
"I'm going to give this up."
And I was offered a job working with animals and I took it.
Now I'm a lecturer in wildlife and conservation, and I don't miss, "Do you want fries with that?"
And one of Cherylin's biggest fans is her sister, Lorna.
Animals have been the main focus all her life.
Her whole life, she's been working towards this, so to win it would be a dream come true.
Over the weeks, her fighting spirit has kept her in the competition.
She could have gone out in week two, week three, week four, but she kept bouncing back.
When you really work with her and give her an opportunity, she rises to it and shines.
Conquering fear of going in the water...
I've never been so scared in my life.
..That was difficult.
That's fantastic.
But her biggest battle has always been with handling the camera.
I am no good with technology.
Press a button on a computer, I have to call the IT department to help.
She's got a big hill to climb still.
She's got nowhere to hide, she's on her own, she'll be driving a team to make the film she wants to make here, and she will be judged on that.
She may be on a mission to find cheetah, but instead, Cherylin has stumbled upon lions from one of the biggest prides in the Mara, the Marsh pride.
I'm having issues with technology.
This could be a good starting point for her film about family.
But to get close-up shots of the lions, she'll need a different lens, which means grappling with her old adversary, the camera.
Sorry, I am wasting your time.
'She was all over the place.'
I almost shook her at one point.
You've been doing this for seven weeks.
You should know how to put a lens on the camera.
At first light, Cherylin sent Anna to film the Marsh pride and, luckily, she's turned up just in time.
You go and find your one now!
The cubs have just joined them, Anna.
OK?
I'm not technical, and I've done this about...three times, four times.
And I'm like, "Argh!
Can't do it."
I hate it.
I'm good at everything else.
ANNA It's quite hard to believe that... we've been put smack, bang in the middle of the Masai Mara and we've got the chance to film lions, cheetahs and leopard.
It's fantastic!
While Cherylin continues her search for cheetah, Anna's left alone to film the pride, and they look like they might be on the hunt for breakfast.
Between the ostrich and the lion, there's a little warthog.
Cherylin's kept the theme of her film to herself, so Anna will have to use her judgment to get the best shots she can.
Is that warthog safe now, Jacob?
No, he's not safe, they're still waiting.
Lions hunt together, slowly moving in for the kill.
It's about to kick off.
Look how close the warthog is.
He's going to walk straight into her.
Capturing a kill on camera is always a rewarding moment for a wildlife film-maker, and it would make a dramatic sequence for Cherylin's film.
Look!
Missed it...didn't they?
Lions will only keep up the chase for a while to conserve their energy.
This warthog has avoided being breakfast.
I wanted them to kill it!
I think for Cherylin's film that will be very good.
Very good footage.
This whole area of nearly 1,000 square miles gets its name from the Masai people who live here.
They herd their cattle in and around the national reserve, and have a complex relationship with the big cats.
James and I are meeting up with a Masai called Harrison to learn more about life in the Mara.
Am I right in thinking the tradition is that the great god you call Enkai...
Yes, Enkai.
..He gave the Masai people all the cattle?
Yeah, we believe that the Masai have descended from heaven with their animals.
And we believe that all animals on Earth, the cattle, belongs to the Masai.
And is it true that because the cattle are so important to you, that you would give your life to defend your cattle from a lion?
For sure, yes.
Have you ever fought a lion?
Sure, yes.
We respect them and they also do respect us.
It's only that when they come and attack our animals, we also attack them and kill them.
So if there was a lion here, the safest place for me is here?
Yeah!
THEY LAUGH Yeah!
Anna's working hard for Cherylin and has remained with the Marsh pride.
More lions have turned up, including a large male.
This domestic spat will be great for a film about family.
Everything that I wanted in my three-minute film has happened this morning, and I've shot all this for Cherylin and I can't use any of it.
I'm very annoyed.
A few miles away, Allen's done just what Cherylin asked him to do.
He's found the three cheetah brothers.
We've got three cheetahs, actually...coming straight towards us at the moment.
It's just wonderful, and it's amazing to be here doing this, when I think I could be sat at home.
I can't fault it, really.
But he hasn't been allowed in on the secret theme of Cherylin's film either, so he can't do any more than get good, clear shots of these beautiful animals.
She's keeping her cards close to her chest, but I'm hoping if anything does happen of any interest, I can grab it and she'll be able to use whatever's of any interest to her.
One of the most famous residents of the Mara is Shakira, a mother cheetah, who is a favourite of Jonathan Scott, who has spent many weeks filming her.
Cherylin is determined to make Shakira the star of her film.
Yeah, it's moving.
Oh!
The story of this cheetah could work well with Cherylin's family theme.
She's had six cubs.
Three have died, two possibly killed by lions, leaving three maturing females in her care.
My family, we're survivors, like those girls will be.
Cherylin is from a big family, but she left home at 16.
I've always had to fight for things.
Coming from a house with lots of people in it, you've got to fight.
"I don't want the last beans, excuse me, I'll get in there first."
We did come from a broken family.
You do look out for everybody and you want to look after them.
She's always remained close to her brothers and sisters.
If you need her, she's always there.
And she's someone you can talk to.
If you've got a problem, you can go to her, and she'll be there for you, no matter what.
Time's running out.
But Cherylin manages to get lots more footage of the three cheetah sisters.
My main thing was, if I found her, I wanted to talk about how females bond and males bond, and I've got three sisters here.
So I'm going to watch the footage and see what happens.
It's important for safety reasons that everyone gets back to camp before sunset, so Cherylin and her helpers today, Anna and Allen, head back.
Cherylin will have to make her final film with the footage that everyone has shot today.
I have huge respect for Cherylin.
I mean, she is a tough cookie.
She could have been crippled by some of the things that have happened to her on this journey, and yet she's dusted herself off, she's got back up.
And you know why?
Because she believes in herself.
Tomorrow, it will be Allen's turn to be in charge, with the other two finalists working for him.
And in sharp contrast to Cherylin's approach, he decides to be very open about the theme of his film.
Basically, what we're after tomorrow, the theme is going to be family.
I haven't actually got a story yet.
I'm hoping you'll shoot me something what I can build that around.
So, er...showing how the family provides...baby-sitting, you know.
Just think of these sort of things - how they communicate, especially with the cheetahs.
If they've got cubs, there might be some communication there.
Tomorrow's really important for me, to prove I'm a lot more than just a good cameraman.
I can see a story, I can develop a story and I can make a good film.
That's what I'm really hoping for.
It's dawn in the Mara and it's time for Allen to start his filming day.
Jonathan will be watching him every step of the way.
Yeah.
You can't ask for a better morning than this to set the scene in.
It's absolutely beautiful.
I thought I'd be nervous, but I'm not.
It's my moment.
Despite his obvious love of nature, Allen's spent all his working life far from the great outdoors.
Before heading to Africa, he was working nights in a warehouse.
I mean, we all have to work and earn the wage.
But I often dreamed that I'd be doing something else, something with nature.
Allen's the least travelled of all the competitors, and had never even been on a plane before.
But he's coped with every challenge he's faced.
He managed to keep filming killer bees, despite being stung as he wrestled with the ropes.
He kept calm in a hot and humid cave as he searched for bats to film.
His camera skills have constantly impressed us, and last week, he captured some of the most dramatic footage we've seen so far.
But Allen, who's more used to a solitary life and weekends photographing nature, has often struggled to stand up to team-mates, even when he's been right.
We can't walk away from that.
Got to do something with it.
There's nothing we can do about it.
Very good call.
'I want to see whether he can genuinely make an interesting film,' or whether he'll just go out and make films that have already been made before.
I want him to step up to the mark and let his personality come through.
In big cat territory, it's important to realise that there's potential danger everywhere.
Here's a question.
How come I can sit this close to a lion.
?
I'm in an open-sided car.
The thing is, she can't see you.
She just knows, and she's known all her life, that cars are noisy.
They smell of diesel and rumble around.
But the silhouette's not human?
No.
But if you were to stand on the roof, she'd go bonkers.
If I stepped out here, same distance away?
You'd give her a shock, and you don't want to do that.
That's stumbling into their world.
Suddenly, they're confronted by you and it's fight or flight.
You wanted to get out and go to the loo, didn't you?
I think I'll hold it in.
Sure?
Yes.
Strong bladder.
OK, if you're sure.
Allen's been looking for lions too, but it's mid-morning and he still hasn't seen anything.
And there are more problems.
The jeep's engine's overheated and Allen's stuck.
We're on fire here.
Smoke.
Luckily, Jonathan's here to keep an eye on Allen.
Getting out of vehicles in the Mara isn't usually allowed.
A big cat attack can come out of nowhere.
It's a little bit of a halt to the proceedings.
But we've no lions just yet.
I'm relying on the girls more than anything right now.
When you're in the field, working in conditions like this, you're not in London, where you can just make a call and fix things, and you just have to adapt to the situation.
Hi, Anna.
How are you doing?
I've found the three male cheetahs.
Wonderful.
'We're having a few problems here with the vehicle.'
So...you know, and we've not spotted any lions just yet.
And Allen's problems are mounting.
OK, we've got a lion, guys.
Sorry to cut you short.
Anna, just one second, please.
We're going from crisis management on the car.
We've got a lion coming.
Right, Anna, you just carry on doing what you're doing.
If anything changes, I'll let you know.
But you're very good to keep going.
The vehicle's ready to go again, and now Allen can focus on filming the lion who's been relaxing with her two cubs.
Oh, look.
It's absolutely... just perfect.
It's fantastic footage for his film and its theme of family.
These cubs are around three months old.
Even though lions have the highest survival rate of all the big cats, only around half will make it all the way to adulthood.
There's stories there.
We just have to wait to see what happens.
You're obviously very, very keen on wildlife.
Yeah.
Is it your biggest passion?
Wildlife?
It's my only passion, really.
What about girls?
Oh, yeah, girls...
I mean, I don't have as much time for girls as I do wildlife, if that's what you're asking!
Allen's spare time has always been taken up by wildlife, something his mum, Wendy, is only too aware of.
I do worry about him and I do think he's lonely sometimes, being in the flat on his own, and I do wish sometimes he'd find himself a girl.
I suppose a lack of confidence and shyness, stemming from being, you know, very little.
Being at school, I was bullied.
So you'd rather just hide away and steer clear of people.
I'm not shutting out the world and saying I don't want anybody, I don't need anybody, because I think we all do.
When he was young, I bought him a camera.
He'd take photographs and print them off, and then he'd draw the animals.
I've got them all over the house, his paintings.
I'm really proud of him.
I can't just take one thing away from this.
I've got many things I'm taking away.
The experience, the memories, the friends we've made.
The whole journey has helped me come out of my shell.
It means that I'm not going to hold myself back any more.
That job is gold dust to me.
I'd love to get it, and...
It'd be true to say I don't want it to end.
I do not want to go home next week.
Anna's been filming some male cheetahs for Allen all morning.
But in the heat of the day, they are content to laze around in the sun.
But Allen's other assistant for the day, Cherylin, is finding more success.
I have found Mrs Cheetah and her three ladies.
It's Shakira, the female cheetah she filmed yesterday, with her three cubs.
That was picture postcard, that was.
This could be great footage for Allen, if Cherylin can focus and keep the camera steady.
Got a cracking shot of the cub peeking out of the tree.
It's like, whoa, wicked, because Allen will like that one.
Allen's got a few great lion shots himself, but little else, and he'll be relying on Anna and Cherylin's footage if he's going to be able to put together a film that will impress James.
I got the cubs up the tree.
Oh, the cubs up the tree?
One's peeking out, like that.
"What you doin'?"
I followed it, and I'm like that - "Oh, my life!"
Cos it just went.
But it turns out Cherylin's shots are very disappointing.
It's hard to say, but don't you think it's over-exposed?
Er...
Do you think they're usable?
Cherylin's camera skills appear to have deserted her again.
But this time, it's Allen who's going to suffer.
Cherylin's not been so good with the camera as some of us.
I've seen what she got today, and she had a bit of a mare.
The action was there.
You could see the animals, but you couldn't see the features really, really well.
Everything wasn't 100% sharp.
'He says, "Oh, you know, some of these, I can't use them."
I felt a bit disheartened.
Tomorrow, Anna will be in charge for the final filming day.
So far, Cherylin and Allen have used very different tactics.
Allen revealed his theme, which was family, which was quite helpful.
If you know your director's theme, you can interpret it in your own way.
Cherylin kept it very secretive and she's just given us a specific shot list.
From the shot list, I was able to guess that she was doing family.
But it would have been helpful for her to say, so that you can interpret things in a different way.
As a result of Cherylin's difficulties with the camera, Allen's got less footage to work with.
But he's staying upbeat.
When I got out here, and it's the Masai Mara, what can you do but enjoy it, just go with it and really enjoy it?
I think Allen's very deceptive.
He could appear as if he was very shy, very quiet.
I'm sure he is those things.
But actually, if you turn the tap on, if you press the right button, there's a lot more there than you think.
I find that very refreshing.
I think he's got a lot of skill.
Don't underestimate him.
It's dawn.
Anna, too, has chosen to make a film with the theme of family.
She's making sure Cherylin and Allen know exactly what's expected of them.
She's clearly thought hard about how she should utilise her team-mates' talents.
She's going to use Allen, the finalist with the best photographic skills, as her cameraman, and try to direct him.
'It's a more intimate way of directing, 'being there with your team-mates, overseeing what they're doing.'
They'll work in the same vehicle.
Anna's sent Cherylin in the opposite direction to try to find and film the cheetah brothers.
She's the only one that's made a different call.
Yeah.
Two vehicles.
Three cameras.
She's going to direct them all the way through.
Ambitious.
It could be a clever move by the 19 year old, who's proved she's capable of holding her own with older competitors in Africa.
Only two years ago, Anna was still at school.
Then she took her first full-time job at Banham Zoo in Norfolk.
Her mum, Kathleen, has always known about Anna's love of wildlife.
She won't get out of bed to make anybody else a cup of tea or empty a dishwasher, but she'll get out of bed for an animal.
But throughout this adventure, she's had to constantly push herself to stay in the competition.
She was the only member of her team to get a dolphin encounter on film in Zanzibar.
That's the best thing I've ever done in my life.
She held her nerve to film a 12-foot crocodile in the springs of Mzima.
And she kept calm at the release of a leopard last week in Lewa.
Anna's the youngest, but showing a lot of promise.
Very naturally in tune with the wildlife.
And she's a good cameraperson.
One question mark about Anna has been, can she direct a team.
I think she likes to sit back and not be up front.
This week, she's going to have to be up front and tell the others what she expects.
She's found the Marsh pride of lions.
It's her first chance to direct her cameraman for the day, Allen.
There's some lions there.
Whether there are...
Jacob, can we head over that way, please?
I think I've seen some of them.
Look at them, they're just...
That's what I want.
The Marsh pride in all its glory is a stunning sight, and Anna's picked up a camera, too, to get the most out of this encounter.
The family thing, the lions' social structure really fascinates me.
Lovely backdrop, isn't it?
A few miles away, Cherylin is on the hunt for the cheetah brothers.
Her guide has heard on his radio they might be nearby.
I have some lead also about the three boys.
That's where I'm driving to now.
You star.
You are a private investigator.
Yeah!
FBI!
FBI.
But it looks like they've just missed a hunt, which would have been spectacular.
Oh, they are even eating.
A wildebeest kill.
They just kill, I think we were just two minutes late.
I've found the boys.
James has told the finalists that he'll be judging them across all three days, whether they're in charge or not, so it's crucial that Cherylin gets some great footage here.
I'm on the wide lens at the moment, which is nice.
I could change it to the long lens, but I don't want to miss any action.
Any time now, you could have the hyenas.
And they will surrender kills to hyenas.
The Marsh pride of lions are providing Anna and Allen with lots of material.
Look at this now.
They've caught a mongoose, and it's caused quite a stir amongst the family members.
Five or six brothers fighting over a chocolate biscuit.
Look, that one behind...
It's gone in the hole.
Anna seems totally focused on the job in hand, which hasn't always been the case at home.
When she was 14 to 16, she was a classic teenager.
I couldn't tell her anything.
She didn't want to do her homework.
I wouldn't say I'm like some hardcore rebel at home or anything.
I'm just 19, to be honest.
I remember work experience, she decided to go to the Raptor Foundation.
I thought it was a cop-out.
I thought it was just her having an easy time of it.
I didn't realise until later, until I saw her at the centre, that the passion was growing.
And it's this passion for wildlife that has made her so determined to do things her way.
The reason I decided not to take my place at university is because, after working with the animals, I realised that I'm a lot better in that field as opposed to an academic point of view.
She thinks that I believe she should be sitting behind a desk.
I actually do not want that for Anna.
I want her to be fulfilling her potential.
I know that, no matter where I go from here, my whole life's career is going to be something around animals.
Because that's what I love and what I'm good at.
Anna's filming day is nearly over.
Tomorrow, the three finalists will find out who will get the job with the BBC's Natural History Unit.
Hippopotamus crossing the road here.
Every day, there's something new and different.
Today has been fab.
I've got some fantastic footage.
Allen and Cherylin worked fantastically for me today.
They've got all the shots I wanted.
I couldn't be happier with what I've got.
About 24 hours left until we have to make the decision.
And it's not a foregone conclusion at this stage at all.
For Cherylin, Allen and Anna, this is the day of reckoning.
Hi, I'm Dan.
With the help of an editor, they must get the best out of their footage, write a script and prove to James they have the potential to be wildlife film-makers.
Allen had the least amount of footage from his day's filming.
Will he have enough to produce a winning film?
Can I have a look at the next shot before I make a decision?
I'm just wondering if any of it's going to work at the moment.
Natural history is my passion.
Whether it be photographing, filming, painting.
I believe I've got enough talent and belief now to really go for it, and realise them dreams.
I think they're seeing the real me.
And I think I'm seeing the real me as well.
Cherylin struggled with the camera on her day.
But luckily, Anna got her some great footage of lions.
One cheetah walking through the grass long.
One cheetah walking behind another.
There.
Will she stick to her cheetah story or change it to include Anna's footage?
Although they look docile and placid, lions are always alert.
Anna used different tactics, choosing two cameras filming one pride of lions, and left Cherylin to film on her own.
But was it the right decision?
I'd love to get the job over Cherylin and Allen.
Although I'm younger, perhaps I've got more energy, a different outlook on things that older people wouldn't have.
But, you know, there's loads of stuff I don't know.
I've only had 19 years of life.
There's lots I'm going to have to be taught.
In Cherylin's edit, the pressure is getting to her.
Can't find it.
It's not on there.
003245.
How many minutes have I got left on the film?
You're at 45 seconds to go.
45 seconds to go.
That's quite a way.
It is.
Ten minutes left.
I know.
And her editor Dan is surprised by the footage she's chosen for her film.
She's got a lot of stuff that she picked out in her initial selects that she's not used.
It's too dark, which is her camerawork.
It was crap, that.
She was completely lost.
She was a bit at sea.
No worries.
Take care.
What's got you in a state now?
You know when you just want it to be just right?
Just for once, just right...
You haven't thrown in the towel, have you?
Excuse me, you know I never throw in the towel.
You managed a burger place for years, yeah?
Yeah.
And then decided you were going to completely change your life.
How many people do that?
Not that many.
Right.
Then you turn up on this, thinking you haven't got a chance, and, week on week, you manage to pull it off.
Yeah, I know.
But that's what I'm like, innit?
I'm that sort of person.
You're a fighter.
I know I am.
So be proud of it.
I am.
And fight.
I am proud of that.
Like a cheetah.
It was only two months ago, nine British wildlife enthusiasts began a crash course in film-making.
Across the amazing continent of Africa, from swamp to desert, mountains to the deep blue sea, searching out and filming incredible wildlife.
For one of them, their wildest dream is about to come true - a job at the world-renowned Natural History Unit.
This week, there's no last chance challenge.
They will be judged on their final film and how they've progressed during their time in Africa.
This, of course, was your last great assignment.
So, we are going to start with Cherylin's.
Ready?
Yeah.
Let's take a look.
Cherylin's film is called Unbreakable.
'Cats - majestic creatures.
'Born predators.
The kings and queens of animals.
'So how have they become so successful?
'How have they earned this status?
'Here in the Masai Mara, in Kenya, it's all about teamwork.
'One family of cats has to work much harder as a team in their early years than others.
'This cat is the cheetah.
'Quite often, you will see groups of related males.
'By having brothers and sisters, they can hunt more efficiently and kill more often.
'So, it is sure to say that family bonds and working together is a real recipe for survival.
'Well, it works in the Masai Mara, doesn't it?'
Now, it goes without saying that we think you've come a long way.
From this point on, though, we want to break down the films, so we would appreciate you being straightforward and honest about how you've done that.
There were a couple of cheetah shots in there which were quite dark.
Yes.
Was that part of the camera trouble you said you had?
Yes, it was.
What happened?
It was my exposure.
A few weeks ago you said you were going to go to bed and read the manual.
Yeah, I know.
And then...
Did you?
No.
Anna shot you some extraordinary stuff of the lions.
Yes, I know she did.
But you stuck with the cheetahs.
Why?
I did stick with the cheetahs because I just thought that was a different sort of relationship.
Did you talk about your theme to your team-mate?
Not really, no.
I think they knew that I was doing "family".
Would it have helped you in your choice of shots had you known?
Yeah, definitely would have helped to know more about it.
I really liked my story.
Allen, shall we take a look at your film?
Yes, please.
Allen has called his film Without A Pride.
'This is the Masai Mara.
'Its endless plains play host to many herbivores.
'This, of course, means the Mara is rich in carnivores and is famed for its big cats.
'This is one of many lion prides that dwell here.
'Hiding in the cover is their sister.
'She has two three-month-old cubs.
'For the first few months of their lives, she will raise them alone.
'A group of unrelated females have been drawn in by the vast numbers of wildebeests.
'But unknown to the young family, they are literally just 200 metres away.
'Should the two young families meet, the outcome could be disastrous - especially for the cubs.
'Outnumbered, will the young mother be able to fend them off 'or will her sisters come to her aid?'
Allen, is that a final-winning film?
I hope so.
I feel I made the most of what I got.
And how was Cherylin's footage?
It was dark, as Cherylin explained with her footage.
Did you tell Cherylin that her footage was unusable?
Yeah.
Were you surprised that you were that assertive?
I probably surprised a lot more people than myself, actually.
I know I can do it.
Thank you very much.
Two films down, one to go.
Anna, let's take a look at your film.
Anna's film is titled Family Strengths.
'The Masai Mara, famous for its big cats.
'The most successful big cats are the lions.
'This pride consists of four females, nine cubs and two large males.
'Although they look docile and placid, lions are always alert.
'Because they stick together as a family, there are many eyes to watch for danger, 'more bodies to defend territory and more weapons to hunt for larger food like zebra or wildebeest.
'Although larger prey feeds more mouths, small mammals offer perfect hunting practice.
'In the Mara, where food is plentiful, and as long as family bonds are strong and true, 'these beautiful cats could continue to thrive for generations to come.'
Do you feel you got the best out of your team?
I do, yes.
I enjoyed the responsibility.
I did really enjoy directing this week.
They came back with some amazing footage and they did exactly what I asked of them.
The first day was really frustrating for you.
Wasn't it?
Yeah, it was.
I would have loved to have used the footage I shot for Cherylin on first day.
I gave my total best to these two because, in order to get the best out of them, I've got to give the best...
It works both ways.
At the beginning of the day, you went out with two cameras in one vehicle.
Mm-hm.
What was the reasoning behind that?
It actually worked out quite well.
Allen was on the tight with the long lens and I was shooting wide beside him.
It worked out well.
Allen, do you feel that worked out well?
From what I did, I wanted to find a story.
I felt sending us all out separately to cover more ground and more cats had the better chance of finding that.
But you know, it's your decision at the end of the day.
You should be proud of the films you made and what you learned over the last eight, nine weeks.
Here you are, and you deserve your place in the final.
The question for us now is trying to split that.
Now we've seen their films, each finalist has one last chance to convince James they're the one for the job.
First, it's Cherylin.
Is her fighting spirit enough to win the prize?
Why do you want to do this job?
What's so important about this job?
I work in education now, and I can tell this amount of people about stuff.
But if I work in television, I can tell that amount of people about stuff.
This is the time to change that career and move it up a step.
It's been tough for you, hasn't it?
Yeah, it has.
God, how many times have I cried?
Quite a lot.
It has been tough, but I always manage to go, "No, you know what?
"I can do this and I will do this."
That's why I am sat here.
Here's my problem.
I'm not sure that any team can afford to have a player on board that you have to keep picking up and encouraging, and picking up and encouraging.
If I'm in a job, I'm not going to be stood there squawking like a baby.
Yes, I have battled through this and picked myself up.
But I am a very determined lady.
I've got really good skills.
And that's why I should win.
OK, Cherylin, thank you very much.
With a storm brewing, it's Allen's turn next.
His camerawork and natural instincts have always impressed, but his ability to lead and stand up for himself has caused concern.
Your strengths.
What are those?
Er...
You know, passion.
I love what I do.
Can you speak up a bit, please, Allen?
Sorry, yeah.
Obviously the camerawork and the willingness to learn.
I could barely hear you over the storm.
How am I going to hear you in a briefing or when I'm trying to get information back from a team when they're going out filming?
You'll have to sit closer!
Sorry...
No, I'm serious.
This is a major problem.
Also, your answers very often tend to waffle on a bit.
You're aware of that, presumably?
Yes.
Definitely.
Do you think that something you can curb as well?
Yes.
Why should you win this?
I still don't think there's anybody in this competition wants this more than I do.
Why, because you don't want to go back to your previous life?
No, I definitely don't want to go back there.
I do believe that, whatever the outcome today, my life's gonna change.
Is your ultimate goal to film and direct your own films?
Yes.
Definitely.
To do that, what's the best next step for you?
Winning this.
Good luck, Allen.
The youngest competitor, Anna, only emerged as a potential finalist in the last few weeks.
Has she left it too late to prove she's a winner?
Passion.
Do you have that single-mindedness?
Is this really what you want to do with your life?
It is something that I really want.
Wildlife absolutely fascinates me.
It's been a passion of mine from a very young age.
Your youth could be a plus or a minus.
I believe my opinion is just as valid as anybody older or younger than me.
My skills and my love lie in actually working with animals hands-on.
Why should you win this?
Because I'm a very passionate about my animals.
You don't have to tell me anything twice.
I'm quite knowledgeable about a lot of animals.
Thank you very much.
Well done, guys, well done.
It doesn't matter now, does it, whoever wins?
No.
The relief of having your one-on-one grilling is over, but the tenterhooks of the final decision are always terrible.
We hate them.
There's nothing more we can do.
It's in James' hands now.
I'll tell you what, they've all come a long way, haven't they?
Three great films.
I really enjoyed all three of them.
I have to say that first and foremost.
I really enjoyed all three, and very different.
That's the most interesting film Allen's made, don't you think?
I think probably the best of the three.
You think his is the best of the three?
I'll tell you why.
He had the least...
The least stuff, behaviour-wise, in there.
But he really drove a story.
What I love is I think he's actually surprised himself.
Yes.
I'm here in the final and I've been in situations where they could have sent me home and I've done badly.
And they've kept me in.
I'm here to win and I can do it.
Cherylin, she's done so well, she's full of courage.
She's very personable.
She's great at getting something out of people.
And she's very organised.
Her logistical skills around those exercises were very good.
When I heard her voice, I thought, "Hang on, I don't know this person."
It was a lovely voice.
She's got weaknesses but she's got huge strengths too.
If I'm the woman for the job, they've got to take it, warts and all.
Anna's film I really liked.
I suddenly understood the Masai Mara at the beginning of her film and then she went on to tell a story, don't you think?
Each of the three people that you've whittled down into the final have attributes that would, together, make you a perfect person.
Cherylin, I would love to take her courage and her indomitable spirit.
Anna, boy, is she a smart cookie.
And then Allen's got all the technical skills.
And he's a team player.
He such a team player that he might actually give the prize away to be nice.
We know they're looking for...
There's something in all of us.
But what's that final ingredient that they were looking for?
I want someone who's, with time, with nurturing, with care, is gonna go on to make cutting-edge wildlife films.
Who can you bring more out of?
There's only one job.
There is only one job.
The crew that's been with them every step of the way gather to hear the verdict.
Here we are at the end of our epic adventure.
We started with nine wildlife enthusiasts.
But, as you've known all along, there is only one job going... ..at the BBC's natural history unit.
Cherylin.
I don't think your film was the best.
But I think some of your camera work really made the grade.
(At last. )
Anna.
You took a while to emerge as a potential finalist.
But over the weeks your intuition with the wildlife has become very apparent.
And you have also shown yourself to be a strong team leader.
Allen.
Who is this rugged man I see before me?
A little bit of a change then?
Throughout this, your camerawork has been very strong, but behind your gentle and considerate team player, has been this steely determination to realise your dream.
Welcome to the unit.
Thank you!
The Masai would like to congratulate you on your success in the Masai Mara.
I feel elated.
This is just unreal.
A chance to work at the NHU is just fab.
This has been the best experience of my life, yes.
Definitely.
The things I've filmed and the things I've done, the people that I've worked with, you can never take that away at all.
And I'm so going to use it in what I do and in my teaching.
I really, really will.
Something happened to me this week.
I probably found myself, you know.
I really, really just feel so much more confident and relaxed.
In a way, I've won as well, so I'm really happy about that.
When it came down to it, I went for the person who showed the most potential and that, without a doubt in my mind, is Anna.
The longest and most challenging job interview in the world.
But I did it.
I got it.